Hair dye has been
practiced for centuries.
But development of dyes
in the last century or so
have included chemicals
that may be carcinogenic,
that may cause cancer.
Watch to see what the
science says about the risk.
"Do Hair Dyes Cause Cancer?"
Since there's typically no way
to reverse hair color loss,
the use of hair colorants
is a mainstay of management,
a practice documented
as far back as 1500 BCE.
While gray hair may carry
a distinguished look
and limit women's subjection
to a sexualized gaze,
hair color constitutes
a multibillion-dollar market
with up to 60 percent
of men and women
in Western countries choosing
to use coloring products,
many of which to cover gray.
For over a century,
aromatic amines
have been
the main chemicals used
in commercial permanent,
oxidative hair dyes.
The primary problem
with these compounds
is that they can be
potent contact allergens.
Product labels often recommend
a small 48-hour test application
to the skin before use,
but it can take up to a week
for a skin allergy to flare up.
They also may cause cancer.
Hair products contain
more than 5,000 chemicals,
and so it's hard
to narrow it down,
but the aromatic amines,
such as para-phenylenediamine,
that are often used in hair dyes
to prevent fading
due to washing,
have been picked out
as a "probable carcinogen."
Before industry reformulation
in response to
mandated cancer warning labels,
9 out of 10 permanent
hair dye products
were mutagenic,
meaning capable
of causing DNA mutations.
This then appeared to translate
into more than ten times
the odds of DNA damage
in breast cells
obtained from
the breast milk of women
who had used hair dye
in the last six months,
compared to
not using hair dyes at all.
But does it translate
into more cancer?
A meta-analysis of 42 studies
found that hairdressers,
particularly those
who held their jobs
10 or more years, were at
significantly higher risk
of developing bladder cancer
later in life.
Hairdressers, beauticians,
and barbers
may also suffer
more lung cancer,
voice box cancer,
and multiple myeloma.
There is some evidence that
hairdressers may smoke more,
but the researchers
took this into account.
They conclude that salons
should be better ventilated,
that gloves should be used.
But how much is that
going to help the person
whose head
has been soaked in it?
Based on testing
for radioactively-traced
hair dye ingredients
in the urine,
experiments suggest that
exposure to hair dye
may be
several hundred-fold higher
in hair dye users
than the occupational risk
to the hairdressers.
But thankfully there does not
seem to be an excess risk
of bladder cancer
among those who just
use hair dye personally.
Furthermore, major changes
took place in the 1980s
to make hair dyes safer.
In 1979, the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
started requiring
cancer warning labels
on hair dye products,
leading the industry to start
reformulating to eliminate
the most carcinogenic
ingredients.
A turning point
in bladder cancer risk
isn't apparent from the data,
but this may just be a function
of the long latency time
between exposure and malignancy
for bladder cancer,
which can be 30 or 40 years.
If you look at
faster developing cancers,
such as leukemia
or follicular lymphoma,
there does seem to be
a drop-off in risk after 1980,
though a 2019 meta-analysis,
looking at
increased
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma risk
without consideration
of date range,
concluded "exposure to hair
colorants should be reduced
as much as possible."
For prostate cancer,
the doubling of odds
associated with hair dye
use seems limited
to pre-1980 exposure,
and there appears to be
no link to brain tumors
in either time frame.
As a tragically ironic aside,
while the risk associated with
hair products may have declined
for white men and women,
the opposite trend
seems to have occurred
for certain hair products
targeted towards
African Americans.
The Black Women's Health Study,
which assessed exposure
in the 1990s,
found no association
between breast cancer
and the use of hair "relaxers,"
chemical treatments
used to straighten hair.
But in the early 2000s,
popular straighteners
switched from
non-carcinogenic compounds,
like lye,
to chemical cocktails
containing formaldehyde.
So now,
frequent straightener use
is associated with
about a 30 percent higher
breast cancer risk.
Thankfully, there's been
a shift towards embracing
more natural hair styles in
the African-American community,
resulting in
the sales of hair relaxers
falling by 40 percent
in recent years.